[
  {
    "question": "The presence of a nonmalignant mid- or upper esophageal stricture always indicates the presence of:",
    "options": ["Alkaline reflux esophagitis", "Barrett's esophagus", "Idiopathic reflux disease", "Mediastinal fibrosis", "Scleroderma"],
    "answer": "Scleroderma"
  },
  {
    "question": "In esophageal atresia:",
    "options": ["The majority have lower pouch tracheoesophageal fistula.", "The pure esophageal atresia is associated with imperforate anus.", "Is diagnosed by contrast swallow study.", "Most of the patients are syndromic."],
    "answer": "The majority have lower pouch tracheoesophageal fistula."
  },
  {
    "question": "A 63-year-old man presented with progressive dysphagia and 20 pounds weight loss. Barium-swallow revealed a mid oesophageal lesion. Diagnosis is best established by which of the followings:",
    "options": ["Endoscopic ultrasonography", "Upper gastrointestinal endoscopy and biopsy", "CT scan of abdomen and chest", "Bone scan", "MRI of the brain"],
    "answer": "Upper gastrointestinal endoscopy and biopsy"
  },
  {
    "question": "A diagnosis of bleeding oesophageal varices is made. The appropriate initial therapy is:",
    "options": ["Endoscopic sclerotherapy", "Intravenous vasopressin", "Balloon tamponade by Sengstaken tube", "Emergency oesophageal transection", "Emergency portacaval shunt"],
    "answer": "Intravenous vasopressin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is correct?",
    "options": [
      "Adenocarcinoma of the oesophagus is the commonest oesophageal tumour encountered worldwide.",
      "Adenocarcinoma of the oesophagus commonly arises in areas of intestinal metaplasia.",
      "Radiotherapy should routinely be used as an adjuvant treatment after complete resection of an oesophageal tumour.",
      "Radical lymphadenectomy is essential to the curative treatment of gastric cancer.",
      "Most gastric cancers in the UK are diagnosed at an early stage."
    ],
    "answer": "Adenocarcinoma of the oesophagus commonly arises in areas of intestinal metaplasia."
  },
  {
    "question": "A precancerous cause of dysphagia:",
    "options": ["Reflux oesophagitis", "Oesophageal moniliasis", "Barrett’s oesophagitis", "Corrosive strictures", "Gastric H. pylori"],
    "answer": "Barrett’s oesophagitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Epigastric pain radiating to the retrosternal region associated with heartburn that prevents the patient from lying down to sleep is due to:",
    "options": ["Carcinoma of the oesophagus", "Carcinoma of the pancreas", "Hiatus hernia with reflux oesophagitis", "Chronic calculous cholecystitis", "Angina pectoris"],
    "answer": "Hiatus hernia with reflux oesophagitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The emergency procedure that stops bleeding from oesophageal varices is:",
    "options": ["Injection of Vitamin K", "Sengstaken tube", "Blood transfusion", "Fresh frozen plasma", "Dextran or Haemagel"],
    "answer": "Sengstaken tube"
  },
  {
    "question": "Severe upper GIT bleeding is due to:",
    "options": ["Oesophageal carcinoma", "Gastric carcinoma", "Mallory–Weiss syndrome", "Oesophageal varices", "Anterior duodenal ulcer"],
    "answer": "Oesophageal varices"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning carcinoma of the esophagus is true?",
    "options": [
      "Alcohol has been implicated as a precipitating factor",
      "Squamous carcinoma is the most common type at the cardioesophageal junction",
      "It has a higher incidence in males",
      "It occurs more commonly in patients with corrosive esophagitis",
      "Surgical excision is the only effective treatment"
    ],
    "answer": "It has a higher incidence in males"
  },
  {
    "question": "Barium swallow X-ray in achalasia shows:",
    "options": ["Rat tail appearance", "Pencil tip appearance", "Soap bubble appearance", "Cork screw oesophagus", "Lower oesophageal ring"],
    "answer": "Rat tail appearance"
  },
  {
    "question": "The treatment of oesophageal varices includes all the following EXCEPT:",
    "options": ["Resuscitation", "Endoscopic sclerotherapy", "Endoscopic banding", "Splenectomy and partial gastrectomy", "Oesophageal stapling"],
    "answer": "Splenectomy and partial gastrectomy"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most common premalignant condition predisposing to adenocarcinoma of the esophagus is:",
    "options": ["Caustic stricture", "Barrett's esophagus", "Plummer-Vinson syndrome", "Radiation esophagitis", "Achalasia of the cardia"],
    "answer": "Barrett's esophagus"
  },
  {
    "question": "A patient with epigastric mass and history of Barrett's oesophagus is wisely diagnosed to have:",
    "options": ["Adenocarcinoma of the oesophagus", "Carcinoma of the stomach", "Carcinoma body of pancreas", "Pseudopancreatic cyst", "Abdominal aortic aneurysm"],
    "answer": "Adenocarcinoma of the oesophagus"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 58-years-old man, with a long history of achalasia, presents with dysphagia that has worsened within the past few days. He has lost 6.5 Kg within 1 month. Upper GI endoscopy revealed a friable mass. What’s the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": ["Adenocarcinoma of esophagus", "Squamous cell carcinoma of esophagus", "Leiomyoma", "Esophageal web", "Barrett’s esophagus"],
    "answer": "Squamous cell carcinoma of esophagus"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 59-year-old man, with a long history of heartburn, has undergone upper GI endoscopy, which showed Barrett’s esophagus with low-grade dysplasia. What’s the best next step in management?",
    "options": ["Partial esophagectomy", "Total esophagectomy", "Endoscopic mucosal resection (EMR)", "Surveillance with upper GI endoscopy and biopsy every 6 months", "None of the above"],
    "answer": "Surveillance with upper GI endoscopy and biopsy every 6 months"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 75-years-old female presents with a 3 weeks history of progressive dysphagia that started with solids, then involved liquids as well. She has lost 5 Kg in a short time period. Upper GI endoscopy was performed and showed Barrett’s esophagus. This pre-malignant condition is associated with which type of esophageal cancers?",
    "options": ["Adenocarcinoma", "Squamous cell carcinoma", "Leiomyoma", "Esophageal sarcoma", "None of the above"],
    "answer": "Adenocarcinoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 35-years-old woman is complaining of dysphagia to solids and liquids, associated with chest pain, and regurgitation of food. Over the past month, the patient lost around 4.5 Kg. The patient is not a smoker, nor an alcoholic. What’s the gold standard diagnosis for this condition?",
    "options": ["Upper GI endoscopy", "Urea breath test", "24-hour esophageal pH monitoring", "CT scan of the abdomen", "Esophageal manometry"],
    "answer": "Esophageal manometry"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding the patient in the question above. What’s the best treatment for her condition?",
    "options": ["Upper GI endoscopy + biopsy + regular follow up", "Laparoscopic Heller’s myotomy with post-operative pantoprazole", "Botulinum toxin injection in the lower esophagus", "Esophageal balloon dilatation", "Esophagectomy to prevent progression to cancer"],
    "answer": "Laparoscopic Heller’s myotomy with post-operative pantoprazole"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 63-years-old male, with a long history of intestinal bilharziasis, came to the ER with hematemesis. His BP was 90/60 mmHg. What’s the best initial treatment for this condition?",
    "options": ["Endoscopic variceal (band) ligation", "Endoscopic sclerotherapy", "IV octreotide (vasopressin)", "Esophageal balloon tamponade (Sengstaken-Blackmore tube)", "Emergency porto-caval shunt"],
    "answer": "IV octreotide (vasopressin)"
  }
]
